Halpern family fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Halpern family fonds
1865 - 1990
F-58
Q100155415
3.07 m of textual records ca. 700 photographs 193 transparencies 40 artifacts 9 contact sheets 7 sound recordings
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of British Columbia through the Archives Association of British Columbia's Community Archives Assistance Program; and by the Office of the President of Simon Fraser University (March 1991).
Halpern family
The Halpern Family fonds consists of the personal archives of five members of the Halpern family: Simon (1865-1939) and Rosalie (1875-1951) Halpern; their daughter Fanny Halpern (1899-1952), a psychiatrist; their son George Halpern (1902-1989), a businessman and philanthropist; and his wife Ida Halpern (1910-1987), a noted ethnomusicologist.
Simon Halpern was born on June 6, 1865. He was a Surgeon-General in the Austrian Army. He died in 1939. Simon’s wife Rosalie Halpern (nee Salkind) was born on November 19, 1875, in Kremenczuk, Russia. She died in Shanghai, China, on June 26, 1951.
Fanny Gisela Halpern was born August 1, 1899 in Krakow, Poland. After graduating in medicine from the University of Vienna in 1924, she worked in various clinics in that city. Her interest in neurology and psychiatry led her to study with Professor Wagner-Jauregg, who had received the Nobel Prize for developing the malarial treatment of syphilis.
Fanny was invited to China in November 1933 to teach at the Medical College of China in Shanghai. She later taught at Shanghai’s St. John's University and Women's Christian Medical College. In 1935 she organized China's first modern psychiatric hospital, Shanghai Mercy Hospital for Nervous Diseases. She became the hospital's medical director, while at the same time serving as a consultant to several other medical institutions.
Fanny founded the first Committee on Psychiatry in China. She also established a Committee on Mental Hygiene in Shanghai, which became the Mental Hygiene Association of that city. The group consisted mainly of volunteers who worked in mental hygiene and child guidance clinics. She wrote many articles on psychiatry and neurology and presented papers at scientific meetings in Europe and China.
For much of her time in Shanghai, Fanny shared her life and home with her mother, Rosalie, who joined her there after Simon's death in 1939. Shortly after her mother passed away in 1951, Fanny moved to Vancouver to be near her brother, George, and his wife, Ida. Fanny Halpern died on June 26, 1952.
George Robert Halpern was born in Krakow, Poland on May 11, 1902. In 1936 he married Ida (nee Ruhdörfer), who was born on July 17, 1910, in Vienna, Austria, to Heinrich and Sabine Ruhdörfer.
George Halpern had a Ph.D. in chemistry, and as a research chemist, developed a number of pharmaceutical and cosmetic preparations that were manufactured in Vienna and later in Italy (1936-1937) after he established a factory there. Halpern's medicines, with such names as "gelamon" and "jonojod," were advertised for the treatment of various illnesses including asthma, rheumatism, atherosclerosis, and syphilis. Halpern's cosmetic products included skin creams and hair tonics.
Once Ida received her doctorate in music in July 1938, she and George decided to leave Vienna. That October they moved to Shanghai to be with George's sister Fanny. While there, Ida taught music history at the University of Shanghai. George considered opening a pharmaceutical factory in Shanghai as well, but instead in 1939 he and Ida left for Canada.
Arriving in Vancouver in August, the Halperns were initially placed under a deportation order. They succeeded in gaining landed immigrant status through the intervention of R.D. Murray, manager of the Chartered Bank of India, Australia, and China located in Shanghai. Murray offered financial guarantees regarding Halpern's proposed business enterprises.
George hoped to manufacture cosmetics in Vancouver, but was discouraged by George Cunningham, the owner of the city's largest drugstore chain, who told George that his stores only dealt with nationally advertised products. Instead, after inventing chocolate-covered cod-liver oil pills for children, George established his own company, Dr. G. Halpern (Vienna) Laboratories, which manufactured the product for a short time (ca. 1939-1941).
In May 1941 George joined the Canadian Fishing Company as a research chemist. His role was to develop products, such as vitamin oils and poultry feed, that could be manufactured from fish. Halpern also joined a professional association, the Chemical Institute of Canada, and became chairman of its Vancouver section. In 1953, the Canadian Fishing Company’s management curtailed its research activities, and Halpern had to seek other employment. In 1954, he opened his own business, G.R. Chemicals, Ltd., which manufactured "Ply-O-Seal" plastic patching compounds for the plywood industry.
In 1969, George sold the assets of G.R. Chemicals to the H.B. Fuller Company (Canada) Ltd. He then formed a new company, G.R. Chemicals (1969), Ltd., an investment business which owned some property and whose principal income came from interest and rent. This business existed until 1986.
Ida taught music lessons in the Halperns’ home and also lectured in music appreciation and later in ethnomusicology at UBC. In 1947 she began recording the music of First Nations peoples of the Pacific Northwest, being one of the first to study the subject. In 1948 she helped found, and was first president of, the Friends of Chamber Music in Vancouver. Ida wrote numerous articles and a few books on First Nations music, and also published some sound recordings.
Both George and Ida Halpern were noted benefactors to two of British Columbia's universities, the University of Victoria, and Simon Fraser University (SFU). They were convocation founders of SFU in 1965, and their financial support enabled the construction of the George and Ida Halpern Centre at that institution. George was present at the Halpern Centre's official opening on May 24, 1989. As well, the Halperns donated several important paintings to SFU.
Ida was awarded an honourary doctorate from SFU in 1978, and was made a Member of the Order of Canada in the same year. She continued to lecture, and to consult on First Nations music for films and other productions. In 1986, the University of Victoria also awarded her an honourary doctorate. Ida died in Vancouver on February 7, 1987.
During his later years, George played a broad role in community activities. He served as President of Brock House, a community centre for senior citizens, which he helped to establish, in 1974, in a local heritage building. He and Ida both served on its board of directors for a number of years. He was also elected a member of the Dunbar-West Point Grey-Southlands Community Resources Board in 1973. The Board promoted the general well being of seniors in the area through such projects as the seniors' housing complex at Fourth Avenue and Wallace Street. George Halpern died in Vancouver on November 28, 1989.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on provenance.
Fonds consists of materials documenting mainly the personal life of the Halpern family but also includes some records relating to George's and Fanny's scientific and professional interests. Activities and topics documented include the Halperns' emigration to Canada, George's scientific research and business enterprises, his work with Brock House (a senior citizen's centre), Ida's community interests, and Fanny's medical career in China.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Photographic materials; Sound recordings; Textual records; Women; Arts and culture; Science and technology
The fonds was donated by the Estate of George Halpern.
Two additional files were created from Halpern material found in the Art Gallery in 2006. No further accruals are expected.
See the Douglas Cole Fonds (F-35) for biographical material on Ida Halpern.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available.
- George Halpern records, 1900 - 1989; F-58-1; 1.27 m of textual records 48 photographs 13 transparencies
  published
  Series consists of records relating to George Halpern's emigration to Canada, and his scientific, business and community activities.
  - Personal papers, 1900 - 1989; F-58-1-1; 26 cm of textual records 48 photographs; Language: Some of the letters are in German; a few letters are in Polish. General note: photographs are located in the following files: F-58-1-1-0-3 (1 photo), F-58-1-1-0-4 (2 photos), F-58-1-1-0-11 (3 photos), F-58-1-1-0-4 (2 photos), and F-58-1-1-0-15 (10 photos).
    The subseries consists primarily of incoming letters from family and friends. Topics covered include, correspondence from the 1930s relating to the Halperns' efforts to emigrate to Canada and also George's early attempts to start a business in Canada. There are many letters from George's sister. In later decades, there are letters from Ida describing her travels and other letters from friends and associates regarding George's philanthropic activities
    Subseries also includes personal papers such as birth certificate, immigration papers, passport, school certificates, and legal documents including wills, power of attorney and tax returns.
    - Biographical Information (1/2), 1939 - 1953; F-58-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
      Textual records
      Open
    - Biographical Information (1/2), 1939 - 1953; F-58-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Personal Papers (1/2), 1902 - 1983; F-58-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
      Textual records; Photographic materials
    - Personal Papers (2/2), 1902 - 1983; F-58-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Correspondence (1/2), 1934 - 1939; F-58-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Correspondence (2/2), 1934 - 1939; F-58-1-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Correspondence (1/2), 1940 - 1949; F-58-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Correspondence (2/2), 1940 - 1949; F-58-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Correspondence (1/2), 1950 - 1959; F-58-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Correspondence (2/2), 1950 - 1959; F-58-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 58-1)
    - Correspondence (1/2), 1960 - 1969; F-58-1-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Correspondence (2/2), 1960 - 1969; F-58-1-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Correspondence, 1970 - 1979; F-58-1-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Correspondence (1/2), 1980 - 1989; F-58-1-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Correspondence (2/2), 1980 - 1989; F-58-1-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Incoming Letters (re Ida's death) (1/2), 1987; F-58-1-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Incoming Letters (re Ida's death) (2/2), 1987; F-58-1-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Correspondence, [19--]; F-58-1-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
    - Legal Documents, 1977 - 1986; F-58-1-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 58-2)
  - Scientific and business activities records, 1926 - 1986; F-58-1-2; 76 cm of textual records
    Subseries includes research notes and diary, correspondence, reports, reprints, financial records, annual reports and other documents.
    - Pharmaceutical research, 1929 - 1938; F-58-1-2-1; 10 cm of textual records; Language: Some of the material is in German.
      Sub-subseries consists of records relating to George Halpern's early pharmaceutical research. Includes notebooks, correspondence, reports, reprints and other documents.
      - Chemistry Laboratory Notebooks, 1931; F-58-1-2-1-1 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
      - Correspondence (1/2), 1936 - 1938; F-58-1-2-1-2 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
      - Correspondence (2/2), 1936 - 1938; F-58-1-2-1-3 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
      - Miscellaneous Notes ("RezepteWinke und Bermerkungen"), 1937; F-58-1-2-1-4 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
      - Reports, Ads, 1935 - 1938; F-58-1-2-1-5 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
      - Reprints, 1929 - 1936; F-58-1-2-1-6 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
    - Dr. G. Halpern Laboratories, 1939 - 1941; F-58-1-2-2; 2 cm of textual records
      Sub-subseries consists of correspondence relating to George Halpern's pharmaceutical business in Canada.
      - Correspondence, 1939 - 1941; F-58-1-2-2-1 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Correspondence, 1939 - 1941; F-58-1-2-2-2 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
    - Fish products research, 1926 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3; 38 cm of textual records
      Sub-subseries consists of records relating to George Halpern's research for the Canadian Fishing Company. Includes correspondence, research diaries, lab reports, publications, and other documents.
      - Correspondence, 1946 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-1 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
      - Diary of Research Activities, 1943 - 1947; F-58-1-2-3-2 (Archival box - standard 58-3)
      - Diary of Research Activities, 1947 - 1951; F-58-1-2-3-3 (Archival box - standard 58-4)
      - Laboratory Papers--Miscellaneous (1/2), 1941 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-4 (Archival box - standard 58-4)
      - Laboratory Papers--Miscellaneous (2/2), 1941 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-5 (Archival box - standard 58-4)
      - Laboratory Reports and Memos (1/5), 1941 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-6 (Archival box - standard 58-4)
      - Laboratory Reports and Memos (2/5), 1941 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-7 (Archival box - standard 58-5)
      - Laboratory Reports and Memos (3/5), 1941 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-8 (Archival box - standard 58-5)
      - Laboratory Reports and Memos (4/5), 1941 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-9 (Archival box - standard 58-5)
      - Laboratory Reports and Memos (5/5), 1941 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-10 (Archival box - standard 58-5)
      - Reprints, 1929 - 1936; F-58-1-2-3-11 (Archival box - standard 58-5)
      - Addresses, 1946 - 1947; F-58-1-2-3-12 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Biely-Halpern Manuscripts of Publications, 1947; F-58-1-2-3-13 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Fatty Acids Information, 1943; F-58-1-2-3-14 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - History of Vitamin A, 1947; F-58-1-2-3-15 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Methionine, 1952 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-16 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Old Papers and Publications, 1926 - 1953; F-58-1-2-3-17 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Pilot Plant Cost Calculations, 1945; F-58-1-2-3-18 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Price Calculation for Dry Vitamin A, 1944; F-58-1-2-3-19 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Vitamin A Analytical Papers, 1945; F-58-1-2-3-20 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
      - Work Connected with Nets, 1947 - 1952; F-58-1-2-3-21 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
    - Chemical Institute of Canada, 1947 - 1953; F-58-1-2-4; 1 cm of textual records
      Sub-subseries consists of one file relating to George Halpern's membership in the Chemical Institute of Canada.
      - Chemical Institute of Canada, 1947 - 1953; F-58-1-2-4-1 (Archival box - standard 58-6)
    - G. R. Chemicals, Ltd., 1954 - 1986; F-58-1-2-5; 26 cm of textual records
      Sub-subseries consists of records relating to George Halpern's later business ventures in the plywood industry. Includes correspondence, formula book, financial papers, and other documents.
      - Correspondence (1/4), 1954 - 1969; F-58-1-2-5-1 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Correspondence (2/4), 1954 - 1969; F-58-1-2-5-2 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Correspondence (3/4), 1954 - 1969; F-58-1-2-5-3 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Correspondence (4/4), 1954 - 1969; F-58-1-2-5-4 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Formula Book, 1957; F-58-1-2-5-5 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Tax Ledger, 1954 - 1969; F-58-1-2-5-6 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Annual Reports, 1969 - 1981; F-58-1-2-5-7 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Correspondence, 1969 - 1986; F-58-1-2-5-8 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Financial Statements, 1977 - 1985; F-58-1-2-5-9 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Tax Returns, Corporate, 1972 - 1985; F-58-1-2-5-10 (Archival box - standard 58-7)
      - Sixteen individual sales ledgers, 1954 - 1970; F-58-1-2-5-11 (Archival box - standard 58-8)
  - Community activities records, 1973 - 1989; F-58-1-3; 25 cm of textual records 13 transparencies 1 sound recording; Physical description: sound recording consists of 2 audio cassettes (file F-58-1-3-0-3). General note: photographs are located in file F-58-1-3-0-4.
    Subseries relates to George Halpern's community activities. Records include correspondence, minutes, newsletters, financial statements, clippings, scrapbook, guest book, and audio-cassettes relating to Brock House. Also includes correspondence, reports, minutes and other documents relating to the Dunbar West Point Grey Southlands Community Resources Board and the Dunbar West Point Grey Southlands Task Force, which was set up to run the election for the Community Resources Board.
    - Brock House Society - Constitution, Agenda, Minutes, 1974 - 1980; F-58-1-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 58-9)
    - Construction, 1974 - 1977; F-58-1-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 58-9)
    - Finance, 1976 - 1985; F-58-1-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 58-9)
    - Founder's Dinner Guest Book, 1989; F-58-1-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 58-9)
    - General Correspondence (1/2), 1974 - 1978; F-58-1-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 58-9)
    - General Correspondence (2/2), 1974 - 1978; F-58-1-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 58-9)
    - Newsletter, Clippings, 1974 - 1989; F-58-1-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 58-9)
    - Restaurant, 1976 - 1986; F-58-1-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 58-10)
    - Scrapbook, 1974 - 1979; F-58-1-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 58-10)
    - Audio tapes, 1976; F-58-1-3-0-10
      - Dr Halpern, February 1976; F-58-1-3-0-10-1 (Audio cassette OBJ-3120, Audio cassette OBJ-3121)
        Sound recordings
    - Community Resources Board, 1974; F-58-1-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 58-10)
    - Senior Citizens' Committee, 1973 - 1975; F-58-1-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 58-10)
- Ida Halpern records, 1900 - 1990; F-58-2; 63 cm of textual records 88 photographs 14 transparencies; General note: photographs are located in the following files: F-58-2-0-0-6 (2 photos), F-58-2-0-0-7 (3 photos), F-58-2-0-0-10 (4 photos), F-58-2-0-0-15 (1 photo), F-58-2-0-0-16 (1 photo), and F-58-2-0-0-17 (10 photos).
  The bulk of Ida Halpern's professional papers are in the Provincial Archives of British Columbia. This series includes inventories of her papers at that repository as well as records relating to a few professional and community activities.
  The correspondence is mainly personal, from friends or relatives, or related to Ida Halpern's volunteer efforts to promote music appreciation in Vancouver through various community groups. These groups included the Vancouver Women's Musical Club, Friends of Chamber Music, Festival Concert Society, and the Metropolitan Opera National Council (for regional auditions). Some related material, such as programs and brochures, is also included. There is some correspondence regarding her work for UBC Extension, The Province newspaper, CBC Radio, and Folkways records. One file, entitled by Ida Halpern, "Fan Mail," contains letters received about her articles, courses, or broadcasts.
  Series contains birth certificate, school certificates, deed, copyrights, will, income tax returns, university records, diploma, curriculum vita, chapter of biography, film proposal, death certificate, obituaries and other news clippings. Also includes brochures, course outlines, notes, and exams relating to some of Ida Halpern's courses for U.B.C. Extension, notes for reviews, speeches, classes and articles as well as reprints of What is Modern Music, and Indian Music of the Pacific Northwest Coast.
  Halpern, Ida
  - Finding Aid to the Dr. Ida Halpern Collection in the Provincial Archives of British Columbia, 1990; F-58-2-0-0-1.1 (Archival box - standard 58-11)
  - Preliminary Inventory (apparently an early draft with some annotations by Ida Halpern), 1985; F-58-2-0-0-1.2 (Archival box - standard 58-11)
  - Preliminary Inventory (incorporates some of the changes proposed by Ida Halpern in early draft), 1985; F-58-2-0-0-1.3 (Archival box - standard 58-11)
  - Two volumes of appendices. (These appendices contain biographical information about Ida Halpern, a selection of articles about her work, and her "Agreement of Deposit/Donation" with the Provincial Archives for her recordings of native music.), 1985; F-58-2-0-0-1.4 (Archival box - standard 58-11)
  - Personal Papers, 1916 - 1987; F-58-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 58-12)
  - Biographical Information, 1986 - 1989; F-58-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 58-12)
  - Correspondence, 1930 - 1939; F-58-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 58-12)
  - Correspondence (1/2), 1940 - 1949; F-58-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 58-12)
  - Correspondence (2/2), 1940 - 1949; F-58-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 58-12)
  - Correspondence (1/4), 1950 - 1959; F-58-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 58-12)
  - Correspondence (2/4), 1950 - 1959; F-58-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 58-12)
  - Correspondence (3/4), 1950 - 1959; F-58-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 58-13)
  - Correspondence (4/4), 1950 - 1959; F-58-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 58-13)
  - Fan Mail, 1949 - 1953; F-58-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 58-13)
  - Correspondence (1/3), 1960 - 1969; F-58-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 58-13)
  - Correspondence (2/3), 1960 - 1969; F-58-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 58-13)
  - Correspondence (3/3), 1960 - 1969; F-58-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 58-13)
  - Correspondence (1/2), 1970 - 1979; F-58-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 58-14)
  - Correspondence (2/2), 1970 - 1979; F-58-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 58-14)
  - Correspondence (1/2), 1980 - 1987; F-58-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 58-14)
  - Correspondence (2/2), 1980 - 1987; F-58-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 58-14)
  - Correspondence, [19--]; F-58-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 58-14)
  - Legal Documents, 1958 - 1979; F-58-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 58-14)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (1/2), [ca 1950] - [ca 1959]; F-58-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 58-15)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (2/2), [ca 1950] - [ca 1959]; F-58-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 58-15)
  - Reprints, 1947 - 1967; F-58-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 58-15)
  - Tax Returns, 1961 - 1986; F-58-2-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 58-15)
  - U.B.C. Extension Courses, 1951 - 1956; F-58-2-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 58-15)
- George and Ida Halpern records, 1900 - 1989; F-58-3; 13 cm of textual records 88 photographs 68 transparencies
  Series consists of incoming correspondence, and legal documents containing mortgage and purchase agreement regarding piece of property in Vancouver. Also includes philanthropic letters consisting of correspondence, drafts and copies of legal documents and other records pertaining to the Halperns' donations to the British Columbia Archives and Records Service, the University of Victoria, and SFU.
  - Incoming Letters, 1938 - 1949; F-58-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 58-16)